Guide to the Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs and Research records, 1968-1995 RG0040
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs and Research records
1968-1995
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Office of the Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs and Research
RG0040
4.4 Linear Feet
Collection includes class schedules, report for the Commission on the Year 2000, posters, correspondence, meeting minutes, five-year plans, committee files, and audio tapes.
Restrictions on Access
Series 2, 3, and 4 are closed to research for 50 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from the Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs and Research
Historical Note
The Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs and Research at The George Washington University, now known as Vice President for Research and Graduate Studies, is part of the Office of the Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs. It was previously known as the Vice President for Research and Graduate Studies (1990-2004), and before 1990 it was the Vice President for Research. The research mission of the University is to create and synthesize knowledge at the frontiers of our understanding and to use that knowledge to address issues of increasing complexity in our world, while strengthening the necessary ties between teaching and research.
The present climate for research at The George Washington University had its beginning in February, 1984, when President Lloyd Elliott asked the University Committee on Research to identify obstacles to research within the University and to offer recommendations to facilitate it. Chaired by Henry Solomon, then Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, the Committee produced the document "Obstacles to Research" in May of 1985. It provided assessments and recommendations on issues ranging from graduate student support to computing and set the stage for many improvements of the research environment. For example, it said, "It is essential that the levels of graduate student support continue to be increased so that we may attain stipend levels competitive with the major research institutions." One outcome was the introduction of special Presidential Merit Fellowships to attract truly outstanding graduate students to GW.
The next important landmark occurred through the efforts of Carl Lange, former Vice President for Research and Administration, and Anthony Coates, former Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs and Research. In May 1989, they produced, in consultation with numerous faculty and with input from the Deans, the document, "Strategies for Research: Toward Growth and Competitiveness." This document served as an initial strategic plan for strengthening research. From it emerged two important innovations: The Advisory Council on Research and the Research Enhancement Fund.
The Advisory Council on Research is appointed by the Vice President for Academic Affairs and is chaired by the Associate Vice President for Research and Graduate Studies. It now has nine members recommended by the deans (CSAS--two, GSEHD, SBPM, SEAS, ESIA, Law, SMHS, and SPHHS--one each); six at-large members recommended by the Associate Vice President for Research and Graduate Studies; and ex-officio members representing the Gelman library, the Office of Research Services, Health Research, Compliance, and Technology Transfer in the Medical Center, and the Executive Dean of the Virginia Campus. In addition, two representatives of the Faculty Senate Committee on Research sit on the Advisory Council on Research and two representatives of the Advisory Council on the Faculty Senate Committee. The aim is to bring together all the best thinking of the faculty and the administration regarding research.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include class schedules, report for the Commission on the Year 2000, posters, correspondence, meeting minutes, five-year plans, committee files, and audio tapes. They range in date from 1968 to 1995, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs and Research. Note: Not all series are processed. Ask staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: one series titled Research records and three series titled Office files.
Washington (D.C.); Audiotapes; George Washington University
- Research records, 1968-1995; RG0040 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains memorandums, policies, forms, publications, and reports. They range in date from 1968 to 1995. The materials concern the Committee on Research, the Committee on Research on Humans (non-medical), funding, publications, budgets, patents, the Institute for Communitarian Studies, and "The Communitarian Reporter".
  - Institute for Communitarian Studies, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - University Administrative Standing & Special Committees - Committee on Research, 08/1970 --11/24/1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - University Administrative Standing & Special Committees - Committee on Research on Humans (non-medical), 06/25/1975 --12/17/1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - University research - patent policy, 01/18/1968 --01/23/1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Office files, 1978-1989; RG0040 Series 2; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series contains class schedules for summer sessions, draft report for commission on year 2000, meeting materials for association of university summer sessions. The materials range in date from 1978-89.
  - Schedule of Classes, 1978-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Includes years 1978-1983 and 1985-1989
  - Posters and flyers, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Association of University Summer Session (AUSS) GWU-sponsored annual meeting records, 10/1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes proceedings, correspondence, planning, expenses, audiotapes of proceedings, and minutes
  - Association of University Summer Session, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    At the University of California, Berkeley
  - Association of University Summer Session, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    At the University of Florida, Miami
  - Draft Report: Commission on the Year 2000, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Office files, 1973-1985; RG0040 Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series contains Research on Humans Committee minutes, Penn. Avenue front door committee, 1973-85.
  formerly acc#50
  - Lamont Star, 7/18/1975-2/9/1983; RG0040 Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvannia Avenue "Front Door" Cmtee, 4/12/1983 - 8/7/1985; RG0040 Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Revised Clinical Practice Plan (Med. School), 1975-1976; RG0040 Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Office files, 1970 ca.- 1992; RG0040 Series 4; 3 Linear feet
  This series contains five-year plans, budget meetings, genetics department, survey on teaching loads, Committee on Sponsored Research, and Graduate Teaching Center. The materials range in date from ca.1975-1992.
  - Five Year Plans, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    All Schools
  - Budget Advisory Team (BAT) Presentations, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    A.Coates, 1990; presented 1991 D. Gross & J. Schauss, 1992
  - BAT Meetings/Agendas, etc., 1990-1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Computer Master Technology Plans, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - SURA History, Bylaws, etc., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Council on Doctoral Programs, Decision for Neuroscience, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Copyright Policy, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Drafting of new policy 1989-1990
  - Genetics Department, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Indirect Cost Information, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Honors Course in Basic Sciences/Mathematics, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Terry Hufford
  - Leibowitz H. (principle investigator), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sponsored Projects Medical School Task Force, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Obstacles to Research Report, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    H. Solomon
  - A Comprehensive Inventory of Finanical Support for Graduate Students at the George Washington University, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Presented A.G. by Coates to the Council of Deans 11/04/88
  - Coates-Lange-Cohen Report-Strategies for Research: Toward Growth and Competitiveness, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Research and Teaching Loads
  - Survey on Teaching Loads and Research Productivity of Full-Time Faculty, 04/1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Senate Research Committee
  - Children's Research Institute Strategic Plan, 07/12/1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Advisory Council on Research
  - General Information concerning the School of Engineering and Applied Science, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Graduate Teaching Center - information on planning and institution of GTC, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Telecommunications Policy Review, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    For the GW Bulletin, courses in telecommunications.
  - SEAS information, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - President Trachtenberg correspondence, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - University Committee on Sponsored Research, 1970-1989 (Box 2, Folder 15)